恐龙曾统治地球超过一亿五千万年
Dinosaurs ruled the planetfor over 150 million years.
大卫爱登堡主持
几乎在地球的每个角落都可以找到它们的踪迹
They occupied almost every cornerof the globe
而它们的体型和大小各异
and came in almostevery shape and size imaginable.
有些恐龙确实非常独特
Some were truly extraordinary.
如今 我们知道霸王龙是游泳健将
We now know that T. rex wasa powerful swimmer...
迅猛龙则是长着羽毛的狡猾猎手
Velociraptors were cunning,feathered hunters,
有些恐龙的行为相当怪异
and that some dinosaurs hadthe most bizarre behavior.
然而 几乎每天都有新的发现
But new discoveriesare being made almost every day
揭示更多关于六千六百万年前地球上生物的故事
that tell us more about lifeon this planet 66 million years ago.
本季的《史前星球》中
This time on Prehistoric Planet,
我们将展示全新的动物
we reveal new animals
和关于它们寻找伴侣的新发现
and new insightinto their quest to find a partner,
抚养一个家庭所面临的挑战
the challenges faced by raising a family,
以及它们间重量级的战斗
and their titanic battles.
带领您穿越时光探访大自然最壮丽的那个时代
Journey to a timewhen nature put on its greatest show.
尽在《史前星球2》
This is Prehistoric Planet 2.
海洋
The ocean.
史前地球上最大的栖息地
The largest habitaton the prehistoric planet...
是曾在地球上生活过的最大掠食者的家园
and home to one of the biggest predatorsthat has ever lived...
巨大的沧龙
a giant mosasaur.
但并不是所有的沧龙都是身长15米的怪物
But not all mosasaurs areferocious 50-foot-long monsters.
躲在珊瑚礁之间的这条叫做磷酸盐龙
Taking refuge in the reefis Phosphorosaurus.
它也是沧龙的一种
She too is a mosasaur.
是最小的一种 身长不到3米
One of the smallest,at less than ten feet long.
它白天躲避危险
She spends the daylight hourshiding from danger.
但每个小时有一、两次它就不得不迅速浮出水面换气
But once or twice an hour, she has todart to the surface to grab a breath.
和所有沧龙一样 它是呼吸空气的
Like all of her kind,she is air-breathing.
和最大的沧龙相比 它就像个侏儒
She's dwarfed by the biggest mosasaurs.
但也是一个致命的掠食者
But she too is a deadly predator...
也并不总是躲在阴影中
and she doesn't always hidein the shadows.
在正确的时机 它会摇身变成猎手
When the time is right,she becomes a hunter.
这个时机就是日落时分
And that time is when the sun sets.
随着夜幕的降临 它的水下世界发生转变
As darkness falls,her underwater world transforms.
这时 数以十亿计的生物 会从海洋深处上浮
Now, billions of creatures will beginto rise from the depths
到海面附近来觅食
to feed near the surface.
地球上规模最大的迁徙是在几乎完全黑暗的环境中进行的
The largest mass migration on Earth occursin almost total darkness
要想一睹其风采我们只能借助特制的夜视摄像机
and can only be seenwith special night-vision cameras.
这些夜间访客中最特别的是一种灯笼鱼
The most spectacular of these nighttimevisitors are a type of lantern fish.
它们那幽暗、诡异的光是由其体内的化学反应发出的
Their faint, eerie light is produced bya chemical reaction inside their bodies.
这种生物发光的闪光可以用来迷惑掠食者
A flash of this bioluminescencecan be used to confuse predators.
从下方望去 这种光能让它们
And when seen from below,the glow enables them to blend with
和洒满月光的海面融为一体、藏匿其中
and hide againstthe ocean's moonlit surface.
但它们躲不过磷酸盐龙
But they can't hide from Phosphorosaurus.
就其体型而言它的眼睛是所有沧龙中最大的
For her size,her eyes are the largest of any mosasaur...
能够看透幻象 识别猎物
allowing her to see through the illusionand pick out her prey.
到了黎明
By the time dawn arrives,
迁徙的鱼群再次沉入深海
the migrating shoal has sunk once moreto the depths.
磷酸盐龙也必须回到白天的藏身之处
And Phosphorosaurus too must returnto her daytime hiding place.
最大的沧龙回来觅食了
The biggest mosasaurs are backon the prowl.
它必须等到夜晚才能再次安全地捕猎
She will have to wait till nightfallbefore it's safe to hunt again.
白天 史前的海洋 为另一种大为不同的猎手
By day, the prehistoric oceanprovides opportunities
提供了机会
for a very different type of hunter.
在北美洲温暖的浅海
In the warm,shallow seas of North America,
鱼的数量几乎和夜行灯笼鱼群一样多
fish numbers can almost matchthe nocturnal lantern fish shoal.
它们对1.83米长的黄昏鸟有着巨大吸引力
And they are a magnetfor six-foot-long Hesperornis.
黄昏鸟虽然不会飞但它已经完全适应了海洋生活
Hesperornis may be unable to fly,but it's superbly adapted for ocean life.
巨大、有力的双脚推动它非常迅捷地移动
Large, powerful feet propel itwith great agility.
任何不走运的鱼
There's no escape for any unfortunate fish
一旦被它满喙利如针尖的牙齿咬住就不可能逃脱
once it's caught by this beakfull of needle-sharp teeth.
黄昏鸟独享鱼群的时间不长
The Hesperornis don't have the shoalto themselves for long.
剑射鱼 又叫X鱼
Xiphactinus, known as X-fish.
进食的机会很快吸引了一大群
The feeding opportunity soon attracts themin large numbers.
它们身长超过5米是海洋中最大、最快的鱼类之一
At over 17-feet long, they are one ofthe largest and fastest fish in the ocean.
剑射鱼长着巨大的嘴一次就能吞下好几条鱼
With its huge mouth, Xiphactinus canscoop up several fish at once
甚至还能吞下体型是自己一半的猎物
and has even been known to swallow preyhalf its size whole.
一开始 食物足够所有掠食者吃的
At first, there is plenty for everyone.
但随着鱼的数量减少 X鱼的注意力转移了
But as fish numbers dwindle,the X-fish turn their attention elsewhere.
掠食者要变成猎物了
Predator is about to become prey.
黄昏鸟只有一种选择:游泳逃命
The Hesperornis have only one option:to swim for their lives.
剑射鱼的速度更快
Xiphactinus is faster.
黄昏鸟更敏捷
Hesperornis is more agile.
但在X鱼眼中 万物皆可餐
But in the eyes of an X-fish,anything is on the menu...
甚至包括自己的同类
even their own kind.
数分钟内 盛宴被消灭得干干净净
Within minutes,the banquet is all but gone...
掠食者们纷纷散去
and the predators move on.
海洋中的危险不仅仅只来自致命的猎手
Danger in the oceandoesn't only come from deadly hunters.
也来自海洋本身
It could come from the sea itself.
这里是史前欧洲岛屿周边的海域
Here, around the islandsof prehistoric Europe,
潮汐的力量给生物带来了挑战
it's the power of the tidethat creates challenges for life.
尤其是个头最小的家伙们
Especially for the tiniest creatures.
这些是菊石的卵
These are ammonite eggs.
成千上万
Thousands of them.
它们被冲到靠近海岸的地方
They have been swept inshore...
岩石间的水坑里
to rock pools.
在这里 它们可以安全地成长
Here, they have the chanceto develop free from danger.
卵很小 每个不到2厘米大
The eggs are tiny,only a fraction of an inch each.
卵中的小家伙们该破壳而出了
Now it's time for the young withinto break free.
它们通过喷射水流来移动
They move by jet propulsion.
但是掌握一项新的游泳技能并不容易
But mastering new swimming skillsis not easy.
到目前为止 这些水坑提供了成长的温床
Until now,these pools have provided a nursery.
但随着退潮 这些水坑被孤立起来
But as the tide retreats,they become isolated.
其它生物可以逃离
Others can make their escape.
但对于无助的菊石
But for the helpless ammonites,
它们成长的温床可能会迅速变成死亡陷阱
their nursery can quickly becomea deadly trap.
在正午的阳光下 水坑里的水开始蒸发
Under the midday sun,the water in the pool starts to evaporate.
如果水完全干涸 它们全会死掉
If it dries out completely,they will all die.
但还有希望
But everything is not lost.
小菊石可以做出壮举
Baby ammonites can dosomething remarkable.
每一只都在努力追求自由这迫使它们聚成一团
Each makes its own bid for freedom,forcing them together.
齐心合力让它们能够作为一个整体有效地移动
The combined effort meansthey effectively move as one.
每一只菊石都乘在这个微小的生命之浪上
Each is carried alongon this tiny living tide,
被身后的小伙伴们推上赤裸的礁石
pushed over the bare rock by those behind...
最终逃到较深的水中
eventually escaping to deeper water.
现在它们等着涨潮即可
Now they wait for the rising tide.
但不是每一个菊石都能逃脱
But not everyone escapes.
搁浅的不计其数
Countless are left stranded...
成为了食腐动物的美餐比如这只火盗龙幼崽
food for scavengers,like these baby Pyroraptors.
其余的则被强大的洋流带到了远离陆地数公里的地方
The rest are carried by powerful currentsmany miles from land.
甚至可以远达太平洋的中心
Even as far as this,the very heart of the Pacific Ocean.
这些中央有泻湖的巨型环形珊瑚岛
These enormous atollsand the lagoons at their center
是数千公里内唯一的庇护所
provide the only shelterfor thousands of miles.
这个罕见的地方是一种薄片龙即蛇颈龙躲避危险的地方
In this rare place, Tuarangisaurus,a kind of elasmosaur, finds safety.
但离开了这些浅水海域情况就完全不同了
But outside these shallows,it's a different story.
薄片龙每天都必须前往更深的海里
Each day, the elasmosaurs must ventureinto deeper water.
环状珊瑚岛峭壁上的峡谷从浅海区通向丰饶的进食地
Canyons in the atoll walls leadfrom the shallows to rich feeding grounds.
这一深海区域不仅吸引了饥饿的薄片龙
This deep water attractsnot just the hungry elasmosaurs
还引来了猎杀它们的掠食者
but the predators that hunt them.
海洋中最大的霸主
The biggest in the ocean.
身长15米的沧龙
50-foot-long Mosasaurus.
从海底被带上来的营养物质确保鱼的数量充足
Nutrients driven up from the ocean floorensure a plentiful supply of fish.
薄片龙长着流线型的身体和四个强大的鳍状肢
Streamlined bodiesand four powerful flippers
有着良好的机动性
give elasmosaurs great maneuverability.
但它们每天的觅食行动让其移动模式变得可以预测
But their daily feeding forays maketheir movements predictable
被一个聪明又耐心的猎手盯上了
for an intelligent and patient hunter.
沧龙是一种依赖伏击的掠食者
Mosasaurus is an ambush predator.
这只庞大的动物用巨大的尾巴获得惊人的加速
This enormous animal uses its huge tailto accelerate with astonishing speed.
这次不太走运
This time, unlucky.
事实上 大多数捕猎都会失败
In fact, most hunts fail.
但这里生活着的薄片龙太多
But with so many elasmosaurs living here,
下一次机会很快就会出现
it's not longbefore there is another opportunity.
借着深色峡谷底的掩护沧龙可以在没被看到的情况下靠近
Camouflaged against the dark canyon floor,the mosasaur can approach unseen...
等待一只年幼、没经验的猎物
waiting for a young,inexperienced individual.
完美的受害者
The ideal victim.
沧龙攻击猎物的力量如此之大
Mosasaurus can strike their preywith such force
光是撞击就是致命的
that the impact alone can kill.
袭击非常迅速薄片龙几乎一定是毫无防备的
It's an attack so swift, the elasmosauralmost certainly never saw it coming.
海洋里的生活很危险不仅仅是因为这些巨兽
Life in the ocean can be dangerous,not only because of giants.
在逃离了礁石水坑的小菊石中
Of the baby ammonitesthat escaped the rock pools,
在大海中存活几个月的不到百分之一
less than one in a hundred has survivedseveral months at sea.
但这几只格外幸运
But these few have beenparticularly lucky.
洋流把它们带到了一个非常宜居的地方
Ocean currents have carried themto an ideal place to live:
欧洲海岸线沿岸的海草床
seagrass beds off the coast of Europe.
在这里 各菊石群的大小差异十分惊人
Here, shoals of ammonites occurin a surprising variety of sizes...
什么形状都有
and shapes.
这种长达1.83米的奇怪巨兽叫做杆菊石
This strange,six-foot-long giant is Baculites,
它们在海床附近觅食
which feeds near the seafloor.
尺寸几乎可以与之媲美的
And almost matching it in size,
双菊石 形状像个巨大的回形针
Diplomoceras,shaped like a giant paper clip.
它们都在这里茁壮成长 因为食物充足
They all flourish here,thanks to an abundance of food.
浮游生物、小甲壳类动物有些菊石甚至吃鱼
Plankton. Small crustaceans.Some even eat fish.
这些小菊石开始形成
These hatchlings are beginning to acquire
成熟后将会拥有的奇特形状
the extraordinary shape they will havewhen they are mature.
突出的螺旋壳表明这些是年幼的回角菊石
The protruding spiral identifies themas young Nostoceras.
这些是成年回角菊石
These are adult Nostoceras.
它们喜欢较深水域的海床
They favor the seafloor in deeper waters.
菊石在史前海洋中蓬勃发展
Ammonites have been thrivingin these prehistoric oceans
时间几乎长达四亿年
for almost 400 million years.
其品种成千上万
There are thousands of species.
属于曾经存在过的最成功的一类动物
They are one of the most successful groupsof animals to have ever lived...
生生不息地活在温暖的温带海洋甚至是两极最冷的水域
flourishing in the warm, temperate seasand even the coldest waters at the poles.
比如这里 南极洲附近的冻海
Like here, in the frozen seaaround the Antarctic.
经过了几乎全黑的一个冬季低垂的太阳开始化冰
After a winter of near-total darkness,the low sun is beginning to melt the ice...
使得这里可以再次接待一种巨大的季节性访客
making it accessible once morefor a giant seasonal visitor.
莫特纳龙是一种奇怪的薄片龙
Morturneria, a strange type of elasmosaur.
它们是暖血动物
They are warm-blooded,
长着一层厚厚的脂肪来保存身体的热量
with a thick layer of blubberwhich conserves the heat in their body.
它们是世界上最神秘最难捉摸的动物之一
They're one of the world's most secretiveand elusive animals.
这群龙来自三千多公里外的南美洲
This pod has migrated nearly 2,000 milesfrom South America
赶在春天来到这里
to arrive here in time for spring.
这是今年出生的小龙第一次遇见海冰
It's the first time this year's calveswill have encountered sea ice.
这对呼吸空气的爬行类动物来说可能是危险的
It can be dangerousfor an air-breathing reptile.
它们只能在冰面有破洞的地方换气
They can only grab a breath of airwhere there are gaps in the ice.
成年龙必须小心地寻找破洞
Adults must navigate carefullyto find them,
幼龙必须紧随其后
and the youngsters must stay close.
这些冰冷的水域为这些巨兽最爱吃的食物提供了极佳的栖息地
These cold waters are an excellent habitatfor this giant's favorite food.
极地的泥巴里富含小生物
Polar mud full of small creatures.
每平方米的海床里可能有成百上千的小型生物
There can be hundreds of tiny animalsin every square foot of seafloor.
把能吃的东西和黏糊糊的泥巴分开是一个挑战
Separating what's ediblefrom the sticky mud is a challenge.
但它们有一种高效的解决方案
But they have a neat solution.
铲到一口泥后 它们会稍微合拢嘴巴
Scooping up a mouthful,they partially close their jaws,
制造出一个巨大的“筛子”来筛选食物
creating a giant sieveto filter out the food.
只有这种动物演化出了如此用途的牙齿
These are the only animalsto have evolved teeth to feed in this way.
莫特纳龙会在这里饱餐整个夏天
The Morturneria will feed here all summer,
直到极地的冬天将海面再次冻结
until the water ices over againin the polar winter.
在温暖的海域 它们会面对其他挑战
In warmer waters,they will face other challenges.
但最足智多谋的动物们总能在史前地球
But the most resourceful animalswill always find opportunities
辽阔的大海里找到机会
in the vast oceansof the prehistoric planet.
揭秘史前星球
(沧龙的速度有多快?)
史前地球的陆地由恐龙统治
The lands of the prehistoric planetwere ruled by the dinosaurs.
但海洋则被一群大为不同的爬行动物占据
But the seas were dominatedby a very different group of reptiles:
沧龙
the mosasaurs.
这就是其中之一的头骨
And this is the skull of one of them.
沧龙是海生蜥蜴
Mosasaurs were seagoing lizards.
可以把它想成会游泳的、鲸鱼般大小的科莫多龙
Think of a giant, swimming,whale-sized Komodo dragon.
加州大学
迈克尔哈比博士
锥形的嘴 粗糙的皮肤 长着四个鳍而不是四肢
Tapered snout, rough skin,four fins instead of normal limbs
长长的尾巴很像上下颠倒的鲨鱼尾
and a long tail that would looka lot like a shark tail but upside down.
这基本上就是沧龙了
That's basically a mosasaur.
最大的是霍夫曼沧龙
The largest was Mosasaurus hoffmanni.
是一种依赖伏击的掠食者
It was an ambush predator.
但它成功的秘诀是什么?
But what was the secret of its success?
它们能在你眼前从完全静止状态瞬间达到极快的速度
They can move from just still,not moving at all to incredible speedsright before your eyes.
南加州大学
基尔斯滕福莫索
在现代世界诸如鳄鱼的爬行类动物拥有这种能力
In the modern world, we seethis ability in reptiles like crocodiles.
它们的肌肉能够提供多次短促而强大的爆发
Their muscles can deliver short burstsof tremendous power.
鉴于沧龙是爬行类动物、是蜥蜴
Mosasaurus, given that they're reptiles,given that they're lizards,
它们的肌肉可能也有类似的能力
probably had similar capabilitiesin their muscles.
它们还有一种适应力
They also had another adaptation
也许能增强出其不意的效果
that could increasethe element of surprise.
游泳的难点之一是
One of the tricky things about swimming is
你需要一种特殊的动力来快速起动
you need a special kind of dynamicto get out of the gate quickly,
就好比短跑运动员从起跑器上起跑
to do the equivalent of a sprinter's startfrom the blocks.
达到这一目的的最佳做法就是把身体弯成月牙形
And one of the best ways of doing that isto bend yourself into a C-shape
然后用身体的一侧去推水
and then push off of the waterwith the side of your body.
如今的鱼采用这一技巧
Fish today use this technique.
被称为“月牙起动”
Known as a C-start,
它可以让鱼从静止不动一瞬间加速到全速前进
it allows them to accelerate froma standstill to full speed in an instant.
速度 加速 秒表
沧龙可能会做非常相似的动作
Mosasaurs likely were able to dosomething very similar,
当然 其体型要大得多
but of course at a much grander scale.
那么霍夫曼沧龙这样的巨兽到底能游多快呢?
So, exactly how fast coulda giant like Mosasaurus hoffmanni swim?
为了寻找答案 《史前星球》团队委托了一个独特的科学研究
To find out, the Prehistoric Planet teamcommissioned a unique scientific study.
直到最近都不曾有人真正尝试
Until recently,no one had really attempted to estimate
去详细地估测这些表现数据
these kinds of performance valuesin detail.
我们是第一批真正试着
Our work is one of the first attempts
把这些动物的能力量化的团队之一
to really put numbers to the abilitiesof these animals.
研究结果十分惊人
And the results we got from thatare really pretty stunning.
(身体长度)
团队计算了四次
The team ran the calculations four times
(12吨 12.8米)
以确保结果正确
to ensure they were correct.
(尾部长度)
四次不同的测试得出了相同的总体结论
All four of the different trialscame to the same overall conclusion.
这些动物能够产生巨大的加速度
These animals were able to generatemassive accelerations.
这条沧龙游过其体长75%的距离
This mosasaur, it could probablyclear 75% of its body length
也许只需一秒
in one single second.
就是说如果那条沧龙离你17米远
That means, if that mosasaur is17 meters away from you,
一秒后 它就靠近了75%
in one second, it will be 75% closer.
第二秒后 它就会超过你
And in the second second,it would have surpassed you
可能顺便还把你吃掉了
and probably eaten you along the way.
被一条沧龙撞到
Being hit by a Mosasaurus would be
有点像被一辆标准尺寸的半挂卡车撞
a bit like being hitby a full-size semitruck.
先不说之后被咬 光是沧龙的撞击
Just the impact of the animal alone,much less the bite that would follow,
就能立刻杀死很多猎物
would kill a lot of its prey instantly.
沧龙的时速达到48公里
Mosasaurs could reach 30 miles an hour
只需一秒
in as little as one second.
可以说 这就是为什么它们 是有史以来的终极海洋掠食者
This is what makes them, arguably,the ultimate marine predator of all time.